hi so today I would like to try to see
that we can talk about a an interesting
concept called discernment and in
particular how discernment seems to show
up in the context of the distinction
between broadcast media and
decentralized media so first let's start
with we'll start with discernment the
concept is a particularly of being able
to make subtle distinctions nuanced
distinctions but clear and with
confidence so in a very prosaic way you
might say that for example a a person
who's become very familiar with and is
dealt for a very long time in say
fashion fashion can quickly and
effectively discern the difference
between a well-made dress and poorly
made dress he or she could tell by the
feel that the fabric is high quality he
could tell by the by the look that the
workmanship was quelle well-done and you
know by hypothesis could also tell them
the the style of construction was also
well done right so this is a discernment
in a particular domain I for example I
have developed a certain degree of but
they just serve different qualities of
coffee I think that is pretty
straightforward and the proposition here
is that discernment is a distinct
capacity we might say that using the
sovereignty model it's a bit like a way
of very fully perceiving with a very
broad and a clear set of distinct ways
of perceiving so it's a you see with
your eyes and your ears and with touch
and by the way with your mind and with
your cognition and then integrating
these very carefully into a clear sense
of what's what so that's that's
discernment as it seems pretty clear
this is not a trivial thing to develop
it takes time it takes actual practice
in the world and it takes an ability to
really clearly listen to all the ways
that you and your body are able to
perceive and send signals in fact one of
the biggest challenges to discernment is
not being able to listen to your own gut
for example or to what might call your
intuition but if you can if you can
really tune into all the different ways
that your body in mind perceive and then
allow those to speak clearly and then
integrate that into a single signal
you've now developed a certain capacity
the capacity of discernment okay so
holding that now let's step to the next
concept the distinction between
broadcast media and decentralized media
so in broadcast media we have an
interesting situation which is I
discussed it in some detail in a medium
post called
understanding the blue church but the
idea is this you have one speaker and
many many listeners so there's an
asymmetry in communication and also it's
more or less one-way meaning that the
speaker speaks the signal goes from is
speaker to the listeners and effectively
no signal goes from the listeners to the
speaker and in general because of this
these characteristics most specifically
asymmetry there's a relatively small
number in the total universe of speakers
and a relatively large number of
listeners and so what happens is is that
the kind of the responsibility or the
division of labor between speaker and
listener shows up with a certain set of
requirements which is to say that your
job as a listener is to listen well to
receive that which is being spoken which
is which is being expressed and to be
able to do something with it oftentimes
to simply be able to repeat it back with
fidelity
the broadcast Miller wood applied in say
news or in say school is of that sort
right you or your job is to hear what
the teacher says and then when tested to
be able to repeat it back with clarity
and that's what we're we're taught in
how to deal with broadcast and because
there's no expectation or a notion or
intention of being able to have
interaction just to say signal back
that's more or less it and so we might
say is that in the camera if it was a
video or a post or both on the
distinction between thinking and
simulated thinking within the broadcast
modality we broadly find ourselves
selecting for simulated thinking that
our job is to be able to do pattern
recognition to build a schema the maps
to whatever was broadcast be able to
recognize when and where a particular
piece of some broadcast information is
being signaled and then respond in
whatever is the appropriate coded
fashion and I'm going to now call that
particular style judgment so judgment is
a little bit like the way database works
and so I I send some signal and the
signal acts as an indicator of where in
the database I'm supposed to look to
find the answer so good judgment
operates quickly it recognizes a pattern
correctly and then accesses the
appropriate location to get the right
answer and then it pulls the right
answer out correctly and so that's good
judgment in that is a piece of simulated
thinking and there's a linkage it's not
obligate but it's very close it's very
closely related between broadcast as a
modality of communication and judgment
as a mode of perception so then when I
now talk about decentralized
communication this is a different
characteristic in decentralized
communication there is and there's a
rough symmetry between speakers and
listeners or express routes and
receivers it may not be fully symmetric
their main you know somebody on say
YouTube has more of a Pareto
distribution or even a power-law
distribution but it's not for closed
case in point this video a year ago I
was not speaking at all through YouTube
and now I am and so the possibility at
least is open for fully symmetric can
access to this capacity to express and
as those of you know who've left
comments the expectation of
interactivity is again at least in
potential very high and in practices
much higher than a broadcast modality so
in a decentralized medium you have a
roughly symmetric capacity and well it's
not fully symmetric actuality and at
least is more in that direction in
broadcast and you also have a an
expectation of both a capacity for
interaction and some realization of that
and so then close the loop that if
judgment has a style of perception maps
to broadcast then what I would like to
propose is that discernment as a style
maps to decentralized media which is to
say that in decentralized media there
are many many many things to listen to
many channels
the number of people on YouTube and the
number of videos on YouTube that I can
choose to interact with is enormous
unmanageable
by contrast take for example the number
of television programs on TV when I was
kid 3 for if you were tuning into the
UHF band what's just a very different
challenge and and so in order to be able
to make sense of a decentralized medium
you need to actually be able to develop
discernment we need to be able to have a
better sense of that which furthers and
that which is not the ability to make a
distinction between a an expression that
is frankly worth your time and attention
an expression that is not and I'd like
in the last maybe two minutes to double
down on that because I I suspect and
expect that one of the great and
powerful possibilities that is arising
now is the development of what we might
call a discernment engine or collective
discernment and here I want to I want to
hold it very lightly and with some
precision so I'm asking for some
discernment what are the things that
seem to be happening a lot right now is
that people who have not yet learned the
distinction between thinking and
simulated thinking between judgment and
discernment are using judgment in
relationship to decentralized expression
and as a consequence what happens is is
they don't listen closely they don't
honor for example that which is good or
clear or helpful in a particular
expression and instead apply the
coarse-grained repeat or or shut down
stuff that happens in judgment and in
judgment is it screwed it has a very
small number of boxes it's very much
plays into the cognitive dissonance or
confirmation bias whereas what
discernment does is the sermon listens
closely to try to suss out the essence
that that which is endeavoring to
express itself and then we're possible
up regulates it because you have the
capacity for interactivity you have the
capacity to point out that which does
connect that which sounds like it is in
some sense true or real deep or honest
and give that more energy get that more
attention and this can be again at a at
the level of said give an expression
like you could choose this video and say
this video has a certain sensibility to
it that I would like to point people to
or I would like to interact with myself
and you can even do it at a finer grain
you can say this particular piece of
what is being said or spoke speaks to me
in a certain way and so in collective
discernment if we can if we can figure
out a way to how to develop that hand it
off what
of happening is there is a gradient if
you recall the video that talked about
Fitness landscapes collective
discernment creates a hill it creates a
new niche it creates a niche for
speaking truthfully it creates a niche
for expressing with honesty and with
clarity and with depth in a way that
broadcast doesn't broadcast doesn't have
a capacity for selecting for those kinds
of expressions and so if we are able to
and if we choose to enter into a
relationship of collective discernment
and if enough of us do and if we use
that the power of interaction the power
to choose to express on our own to
identify and upregulate that which
furthers and who point attention away
from that which does not we should
expect that we will begin to see more of
that which we we like that way that's
what we want that which we need unless
that which we do not and so we begin to
get an interesting sense of how the lid
closes here that the the first
requirement or the first step is to
become capable of discernment to become
capable of know to sing for example what
are the limits of your own sovereignty
when are you reacting to things when are
you shifting into a judgment perception
schema and not listening but rather
simply categorizing and reacting to
things that oftentimes we're not even
yours to begin with and when are you
listening with discernment and then
skillfully adding your insight and your
attention your wisdom to those things
that should be brought more broadly and
shared more fully unconsciously I think
that's all